A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Tech Review Panel, 2007-2009 (bulk 2007)
Library of Virginia
- Series II. Files of TriData, a Division of System Planning Corporation, 2007., Extent: 5.78 cubic feet (17 boxes) and 1766 emails. (Box 5-21)
  - Series II. Files of TriData, Subseries B. Confidential Seung Hui Cho Documents, 2007 (transmitted)., Extent: 0.53 cu. ft. (boxes 9-10)
    This subseries contains confidential documents about Seung Hui Cho including his educational records, medical records, 2005 commitment hearing and autopsy report. Cho's family gave written consent to Virginia Tech and the Fairfax County Public Schools for those entities to release education and medical records to the Virginia Tech Review Panel. The disclosures were made to the Panel that the records would not be disclosed to third parties or the public. This subseries includes health records and personal information that is restricted for 75 years by the Code of Virginia (Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act, Virginia Public Records Act, and Virginia Health Records Privacy Act). Restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection.
    - Medical Records of Seung Hui Cho, Carilion New River Valley Medical Center and Carilion Saint Alban's Behavioral Health, December 2005, transmitted to Hollis Stambaugh (TriData) from Carole M. Agee, Associate General Counsel, Carilion, 6 July 2007. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Fairfax County Public Schools,, 2000-2001, transmitted to Hollis Stambaugh (TriData) from Anne McCully Murphy, Division Counsel, 3 July 2007. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Fairfax County Public Schools, 1999-2003, transmitted to Hollis Stambaugh (TriData) from Anne McCully Murphy, Division Counsel, 3 July 2007. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Fairfax County Public Schools, 2000-2003, transmitted to Hollis Stambaugh (TriData) from Anne McCully Murphy, Division Counsel, 3 July 2007. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Medical Records of Seung Hui Cho, Cook Counseling Center, transmitted to Colonel W. Gerald Massengill by Charles W. Steger, President Virginia Tech University, 19 June 2007. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Audio cassette recording of Seung Hui Cho's commitment hearing conducted by Special Justice Paul M. Barnett on 14 December 2005 [RESTRICTED]. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Medical Record of Seung Hui Cho, Virginia Tech's Schiffert Health Center and Cook Counseling Center, 2004-2006, transmitted to Colonel W. Gerald Massengill by Kim O'Rourke, Chief of Staff to Virginia Tech President, 12 June 2007. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Medical Records of Seung Hui Cho, Cook Counseling Center, December 2005, copy provided to Diane Strickland, with notes by Hollis Stambaugh, undated. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Medical Records of Seung Hui Cho, Dr. Byung-In Lee (Cho's primary care physician), 2003 and transmitted to Hollis Stambaugh, July 2007. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Tech Policy Department report on Cho, 27 November 2005 (faxed copy to Diane Strickland). (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Autopsy Report of Seung Hui Cho, 19 April 2007. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Poem, March 2006; Virginia Tech Transcript, 2007. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Poem, March 2006. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Education Records of Seung Hui Cho, Emails between Cho and professors/emails concerning Cho; includes several of Cho's writings, 2005-2007. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Series II. Files of TriData, Subseries C. Collected Documents Related to the Investigation, 2007., Extent: 3.85 cu. ft. (boxes 11-21) and 1766 emails
    This series contains records related to the work of the Virginia Tech Review Panel. Included are correspondence from the general public (mailed and submitted through Panel's web page), newspaper clippings, correspondence from the general public (submitted through the Office of the Governor's web page), email correspondence from Department of Health employees between 16-24 April 2007; reference files; and files of TriData staff members including: Philip Schaenman, President, TriData and Virginia Tech Review Panel staff director, Hollis Stambaugh, Jim Kudla, Maria Argabright, Shania Flagg, and Teresa Copping. Copping's files appear to be copies of records from other parts of the collection. This subseries includes legal advice, health records, and personal information that is restricted for 75 years by the Code of Virginia (Virginia Government Data Collection and Dissemination Practices Act, Virginia Public Records Act, Virginia Health Records Privacy Act). Restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection.
    Notable paper documents include: Office of the Inspector General for Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Investigation of April 16, 2007 Critical Incident at Virginia Tech OIG Report 140-07 (Preliminary Report, 2007 (b11, f1); List of suggested questions to ask when interviewing Seung-Hui Cho's family, (b11, f18); After Action Review, Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, Virginia Tech Shootings; Notes from interview with Dr. Marcella Fierro, Chief Medical Examiner, conducted by Carroll Ann Ellis (VTRP) and Darryl Sensenig (TriData) on 25 May 2007 (b12, f9 and b17, f1); copies of emails from employees of the Virginia Department of Health documenting their response to the shooting (b13-b14); and Memorandum to James A. Hyatt, Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, Virginia Tech, dated 4 June 2007, from Larry Hincker, Associate Vice President for University Relations, Communications related to April 16 (b15, f3).
    - Files from Paul Barnett, Special Justice, 2007 (OIG background notes). (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Book and DVD Psychiatry: An Industry of Death, mailed to the Panel by Russ Troxel, August 2007. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Notes by Cho's roommate and resident assistant, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Tech Review Panel background, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Contacts with Families of Deceased, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Organizations at Virginia Tech, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - EE05-Virginia Tech] EMS issues (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - [EE05-Virginia Tech] Law Enforcement (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - [EE05-Virginia Tech] Press File (news clips) (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - [EE05-Virginia Tech] Psychological Issues/CIS (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - [EE05-Virginia Tech] Timeline (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Programs Related to Crime Victims (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Website: Law Enforcement and Tech Response (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Website: Weird Emails (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Website: Warning/Notification (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Mental Health Screening/Monitoring (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - University of Maryland Campus Security (Campus Safety and Security in the Wake of Virginia Tech) (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Interview of Cho Family (list of suggested questions only) (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence to Panel, May 2007. (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence to the Office of the Governor, June 2007. (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper Clippings
      - Concerning Guns (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Other/General (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - Campus Security (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - Regarding Panel (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - Complete Sections on Tech (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Victims (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Student/Response (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Mental Health (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Seung Hui Cho (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Commission on Mental Health Law Reform, 2006. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Active Shooter (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Review of the Virginia Community Services Board Emergency Services Program (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - After Action Review, Office of the Chief Medical Examiner, Virginia Tech Shootings (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Fatality Plan for the Office of the Chief Medical Examiner (OCME) (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous documents related to victim needs in the aftermath of mass fatalities (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Responding to Disruptive Behavior or Threatening Student Behavior: A Guide for Faculty (Virginia Tech) (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Presidential Internal Review: Working Group Report on the Interface between Virginia Tech Counseling Services, Academic Affairs, Judicial Affairs and Legal Systems, Presented to President Charles Steger, 17 August 2007 (2 copies). (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Information and Communications Infrastructure: Confidential Presidential Working Paper, 17 August 2007. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Security Infrastructure Working Group Report, Presidential Working Paper, 17 August 2007. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - [Florida] Gubernatorial Task Force for University Campus Safety: Report on Findings and Recommendations, 24 May 2007. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Email sent/received by Robert C. Parker, SW Regional Public Information Officer, Virginia Department of Health, 16-19 April 2007. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Email sent/received by Robert B. Stroube, State Health Commissioner, Virginia Department of Health, 16-20 April 2007. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Email sent/received by Bob Mauskapf, State Emergency Planning Coordinator, Virginia Department of Health, 16-24 April 2007. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Email sent/received by Bob Mauskapf, State Emergency Planning Coordinator, Virginia Department of Health, 16-24 April 2007. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Email sent/received by the Virginia Department of Health, 16-19 April 2007 (part one of three). (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Email sent/received by the Virginia Department of Health, 16-19 April 2007 (part two of three). (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Email sent/received by the Virginia Department of Health, 16-19 April 2007 (part three of three). (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Email sent/received by Steve Harrison, Virginia Department of Health, 16-20 April 2007. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Email sent/received by Charles Devine, Director, Southside Health District, 16 April 2007. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Email sent/received by Jody Hershey, New River Health District, 16-20 April 2007. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Email sent/received by Steve Davis, Virginia Department of Health, 16-18 April 2007. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (pro-gun), April-May 2007. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (mental health laws), April-May 2007. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (campus safety), April 2007. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (suggestions), April-May 2007. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (general comment), April-May 2007. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Email submitted to the Office of the Governor (miscellaneous comments), April-May 2007. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Constituent Correspondence submitted to the Office of the Governor, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Constituent Correspondence submitted to the Office of the Governor, 2007. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Constituent Correspondence submitted to the Office of the Governor, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Constituent Correspondence submitted to the Office of the Governor, 2007. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Memorandum to James A. Hyatt, Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, Virginia Tech, from Larry Hincker, Associate Vice President for University Relations, Communications related to April 16, 4 June 2007. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Virginia Tech Emergency Response Plan, May 2005. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Tech Emergency Response Plan, Appendix A-M, May 2005. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Tech Emergency Response Plan, Appendix N-P, May 2005. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Reference Material, Mental Health, 2007. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Reference Material, Mental Health, 2007. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Reference Material, Mental Health, 2007. (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2007. (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Letters to Deceased Victims' Families, 30 May 2007. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Letters Received from VTRP P.O. Box, April-May 2007. (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Letters Received from VTRP P.O. Box, June 2007. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Letters Received from VTRP P.O. Box, July 2007. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Letters Received from VTRP P.O. Box, August 2007. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence from VTRP Web Site, 2007. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - II.C.1. TriData, Files of Phil Schaenman, 2007., Extent: 0.70 cu. ft. (boxes 16-17)
      The files of Philip Schaenman, President, TriData and Virginia Tech Review Panel staff director contains panel meeting notes, notes from meetings with officials at Virginia Tech and EMS, reference material, and drafts of the report. Notable records include: Schaeman's handwritten notes from meetings of the Virginia Tech Review Panel (b16, f4); and interview notes from 20 July 2007 with Cho's parents (b17, f8).
      - Correspondence, April-July 2007. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, July-August 2007. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - First Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 10 May 2007. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Second Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 21 May 2007. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Third Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 11 June 2007. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Tri-Data Meeting-Security and Communications, Virginia Tech, 20 June 2007. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Fourth Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 18 July 2007. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Emergency Management Services (EMS) notes from interviews conducted by Dr. Marcus Martin (Virginia Tech Review Panel) and Dr. Harold Cohen (TriData), April-June 2007. (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Preliminary drafts, Chapter IX. Office of the Chief Medical Examiner (with reference material), April-August 2007. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Reference Material, Miscellaneous, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Reference Material, Guns, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Reference Material, Campus Violence, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Reference Material, Law Enforcement, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Meeting Material, Hearing at Washington and Lee University with Council of Independent Colleges in Virginia, Inc., chaired by Dr. Gordon Davis and Diane Strickland, 15 June 2007. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Meeting Material, Virginia Tech Panel Meeting at American Council on Education, chaired by Governor Tom Ridge and Dr. Gordon Davies, 27 June 2007. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Reference Material, Campus Security, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous Reports and Interview Notes, 2007. (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Partial Draft Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, July-August 2007. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Draft Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - II.C.2. TriData, Files of Hollis Stambaugh, April-September 2007., Extent: 664 emails
      The files of Hollis Stambaugh, Virginia Tech Review Panel deputy director, contains 664 emails sent and received between April and September 2007. This content can be accessed online. There are 24 confidential emails that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Stambaugh's unrestricted email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: gathering information about Cho; comments submitted to the Panel via the Virginia Tech Review Panel website; Panel meetings; news articles; and interviews (lists and notes).
      Notable email includes: email from Phil Schaenman, dated 25 June 2007, to Hollis Stambaugh forwarding an email from Andrew Goddard about the Colin Goddard and Emily Haas 911 phone call; email from Hollis Stambaugh, dated 13 July 2007, to Roger Depue and Bela Sood, describing her attempt to get Cho's records from the Multicultural Center for Human Services; email from Carroll Ann Ellis, dated 3 August 2007, to Daryl Sensenig, Hollis Stambaugh, and Phil Schaenman, transmitting memo from Dr. Marcella Fierro, Virginia State Medical Examiner; email thread between Hollis Stambaugh and Phil Schaenman, dated 23, 26 July 2007 in which Stambaugh describes a phone call with Virginia Tech Police Chief Wendell Flinchum; email thread between Hollis Stambaugh and Wade Smith, dated 5, 7 August 2007, requesting information about Cho's credit card bill; email from Bela Sood, dated 21 July 2007, to Diane Strickland containing a document with Cho's Facebook messages; email from Diane Strickland, dated 21 July 2007, to Bela Sood and Hollis Stambaugh, transmitting notes of interviews with Niki Giovanni, Professor of English at Virginia Tech (9 July 2007) and Ray Crouse, Independent Examiner (12 July 2007); email from Diane Strickland, dated 10 July 2007, to Bela Sood and Hollis Stambaugh, transmitting note from interview of Carl Bean, Cho's technical writing professor in the spring of 2006 (9 July 2007); email from Diane Strickland, dated 26 July 2007, to Bela Sood and Hollis Stambaugh, transmitting notes from interview with Maggie Bowman a VT student who interacted with Cho (26 July 2007); email from Diane Strickland, dated 23 July 2007, to Bela Sood and Hollis Stambaugh, transmitting notes from interview with Mike Turner, Clinical Support Representative, Carilion St. Albans (23 July 2007); email from Roger Depue, dated 8 July 2007, to Hollis Stambaugh transmitting his suggested interview questions for Cho's family; Email from Hollis Stambaugh, dated 11 June 2007, to Virginia Tech Review Panel, transmitting a letter from John W. Hammaren, father of Caitlin; email from Gordon Davies, dated 11 July 2007, to Diane Strickland, transmitting notes from interview with Melissa Trotman, Cho's Resident Advisor in 2005-06; email from Diane Strickland, dated 7 July 2007, to Gordon Davies, transmitting notes from interviews with Joseph Aust, Cho's roommate in 2006-07, and Austin Morton, Cho's RA in 2006-07; two emails from John Eide, dated 17 July 2007, containing Facebook messages Eide received from Cho in the fall of 2006; and email from Daryl Sensenig, dated 29 May 2007, to Ellis, containing notes from 25 May 2007 interview of Dr. Marcella Fierro, Virginia State Medical Examiner.
      Email correspondents include: Gordon Davies, Roger Depue, Carroll Ann Ellis, Jim Kudla, Gerald Massengill, Lenwood McCoy, Amy Sabrin, Phil Schaenman, Bela Sood, Diane Strickland, and Tracy Tisbo.
    - II.C.3. TriData, Files of Jim Kudla, April-September 2007., Extent: 778 emails
      The files of Jim Kudla, System Planning Corporation, Vice President, Communications and Information Solutions, and Virginia Tech Review Panel information officer, contain 778 emails sent and received between April and September 2007. Kudla's email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: news articles; comments on chapter drafts; media inquiries; Panel meetings; writing of report; Panel access to material Cho mailed to NBC; and press advisories and releases.
      Notable email includes: email thread dated 29-30 August 2007 on the leak of the final report to the New York Times and the Governor's Office decision to post it online; email thread between Panel members and Phil Schaenman, dated 7 August 2007 expressing concerns about the editing of the report; and email from Phil Schaenman, dated 29 August 2007, to Jim Kudla, discussing who had access to report prior to leak to New York Times.
      Email correspondents include: Teresa Copping, Tim Craig, Gordon Davies, Carroll Ann Ellis, Kevin Hall, Larry Hincker, Ben Huson, Marcus Martin, Gerald Massengill, Bill McKelway, Larry Roberts, Amy Sabrin, Phil Schaenman, Delacey Skinner, Bela Sood, and Hollis Stambaugh.
    - II.C.4. TriData, Files of Teresa Copping, 2007., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (boxes 19-21) and 208 emails
      The files of Teresa Copping, executive assistant, TriData, include multiple drafts of chapters and the Virginia Tech Panel's final report to Governor Kaine, and 208 email. The chapter drafts contain notes that may have been written by Phil Schaenman. Copping may have used these notes to update chapter drafts on behalf of the Panel. Restricted documents have been sealed but have not been removed from the collection.
      Copping sent and receieved 208 emails between May and September 2007 that can be accessed online. There is one confidential email that is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Restricted material includes privileged records (attorney-client communications and attorney work product). Copping's unrestricted email is accessible online.
      Email subjects include: news articles; panel meetings (agendas and presentations); and lists of interviews conducted by panel.
      Notable email includes: email from Copping, dated 1 August 2007, to Phil Schaenman transmitting Bela Sood's notes on Cho's history including interview notes with Cho's parents; email from Copping, dated 1 August 2007, to Phil Schaenman transmitting interview notes with Cook Counseling Center and Care team staff; email from Copping, dated 1 August 2007, transmitting transcript of Bela Sood's presentation to open panel on 18 July 2007; and email from John Hammaren, father of Caitlin Hammaren, dated 11 June 2007, to Teresa Copping transmitting Hammaren's comments to Panel.
      Email correspondents include: Carroll Ann Ellis, Jim Kudla, Lenwood McCoy, Phil Schaenman, Bela Sood, and Hollis Stambaugh.
      - First Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 10 May 2007. (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Second Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 21 May 2007. (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Third Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 11 June 2007. (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Fourth Public Meeting of Virginia Tech Incident Review Panel, 18 July 2007 (and closed meeting 19 July 2007). (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Tech Clips after the Presentation of the Report, August-September 2007. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - News Articles, May-September 2007. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, April-September 2007. (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Contacts with Families of the Deceased, 2007. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Seung Hui Cho' History, 2007. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Road to Hope and Safety From the "First" Juvenile Court, undated. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Information and Communications Infrastructure: Appendices, Confidential Presidential Working Paper, 17 August 2007. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Draft Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, 18 August 2007. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, July-August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, July-August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Drafts of Various Chapters of the Report of Mass Shootings at Virginia Tech, April 16, 2007: Report of the Virginia Tech Review Panel presented to Governor Kaine, August 2007. (Box 21, Folder 3)